Guide to the Office for Institutional Equity records, 1962-ongoing
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Office for Institutional Equity records 1962-ongoing
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Office for Institutional Equity.
4.4 Linear Feet 3000 Items
The Equal Opportunity Office was created in 1972 by Chancellor John S. Blackburn to ensure University compliance with equal opportunity and affirmative action legislation.
Collection contains material pertaining to the Office for Institutional Equity including Duke University's Affirmative Action plans, and promotional material as well as planning and committee material for the annual Martin Luther King Day Commemoration. Materials in the collection range in date from 1962-ongoing.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The Office for Institutional Equity records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1997-2002; 2005-2008.
Historical Note
The Equal Opportunity Office was created in 1972 by Chancellor John S. Blackburn to ensure University compliance with equal opportunity and affirmative action legislation. The office reported to the Chancellor (until 1985) and was originally directed by George S. Kantor. In 1982, the office was renamed the Opportunity Development Center. In 1985 the office was abolished by then-President Brodie, however the functions of the office were still carried out by the former director Dolores S. Burke, who was named Special Assistant to the President, and later, Special Advisor to the Executive Vice President for Administration. In 1995, the responsibilities were transferred to the newly created Office of the Vice President for Institutional Equity. The name of the office changed to Office for Institutional Equity in the 2004/2005 academic year.
Collection Overview
Collection contains material pertaining to the Office for Institutional Equity including Duke University's Affirmative Action plans, files relating to the Ivy League Plus Affirmative Action, Equal Opportunity and Diversity Officers fall meeting held at Duke University, promotional material as well as planning and committee material for Martin Luther King Day Commemoration. Major subjects present include affirmation action, equal opportunity, Martin Luther King Jr., civil rights, minorities, and employment. Materials in the collection range in date from 1962-ongoing.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Affirmative action programs -- North Carolina -- Durham
Civil Rights
Discrimination in employment -- North Carolina -- Durham
Duke University -- Employees
Duke University. Equal Opportunity Office.
Duke University. Opportunity Development Center
Employment
Minorities -- Employment -- North Carolina -- Durham
Separated Material
The following posters were placed in the University Archives poster collection:
Institutional Equity, Call and Response: Listening, Learning and Living the Legacy, January 2006
Seventh Annual Martin Luther King, Jr. Celebration, 12 January 1996
Related Material
Equal Employment Opportunity Committee records, 1969-1973.
University Archives, Duke University.
Vice President and Vice Provost records, 1990-1995.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 1962-ongoing, 6 Boxes
  - Affirmative Action Plans, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1981, 1988
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1997/1998 c.2
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 2001
  - Affirmative Action Plan, Executive summary, 2001
  - Affirmative Action Plan for Veterans and Persons with Disabilities, 2001
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1 July 1973 (Appendices)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1973, c.2 (Incomplete)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1976 (Appendices)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, 1978, (Appendix Supplements)
  - Affirmative Action Plan, Exhibits and Appendix, September 1981
  - Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action Annual Reports nos. 1-4, 1975-1978 (2 folders)
  - Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action Annual Reports nos. 5-10, 1978-1984 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Equal Opportunity and Affirmative Action Annual Reports nos. 2-10, c.2 (3 folders)
  - Clippings, Equal Opportunity Office/Opportunity Development Center, 1973-1978 (Box 3)
  - Committee Composition, 1974-1975
  - Compliance Reports, 1962-1967
  - Discrimination Survey - Females, 1974
  - EEO Advisory Group, 1975-1976 (2 folders)
  - EEO-1 Report, 1967-1974 (9 folders)
  - EEO-6 Report, General, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - EEO-6 Report, 1975, 1977, 1979 (3 folders)
  - EEOC Review of Except Staff ($15,000 and under) University Non-Academic by Employment Practices Associates, Inc., May 1973
  - Employment Practices Associates, Inc., May 1972-1975
  - Equal Opportunity Office, General, 1974-1991
  - Ivy League Plus Affirmative Action, Equal Opportunity, and Diversity Officers Conference, 2005
  - Martin Luther King, Jr. Commemoration Committee, 2004-2005
  - Management Information for Equal Opportunity, 1994
  - Maternity Leave Report, 1976-1979
  - Printed Matter, 1994, undated (Box 5)
  - Section 503 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973/ Handicapped Survey, 1976
  - Statistics, 1984-1985
  - Student Employment, 1975-1977
  - United Methodist Hana Survey, 1978
  - Years of Progress: A Report on Equal Opportunity, 1990
  - Martin Luther King Jr., Commemoration at Duke University (Box 6)
    - MLK Planning Committee, 1999-2000
    - MLK events, 1996
    - MLK events, 1997
    - Memo, February 19, 1998 (re: proposal to make Martin Luther King Day a full University holiday)
    - MLK events, 1999
    - MLK events, 2000
    - MLK events, 2001
    - MLK events, 2005
    - MLK events, 2006
    - MLK events, 2007
    - MLK events, 2008
    - MLK events, 2010
    - MLK events, 2011
    - MLK Event Posters, 2000, 2006 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - 50th Commemoration of Integration, 2012 (2 folders)
  - 50th Commemoration of Integration, 2013 (2 folders)
  - 50th Commemoration of Integration: Final Weekend, 2013
  - Duke-Durham Music Fest, 2013
  - Poster - Brown vs. Board of Education 1954-2004: Conversations Across Generations, 2004 Apr. 17 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Poster - Beyond the Comfort Zone: Race, Sex, and God, undated (Opaperfolder 1)